<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The religion established by law, asserted to conduce most to the true interest of prince and subject as it was delivered in a charge, at the general quarter sessions of the peace, held at the borough of Newark, for the county of Nottingham, by adjournment for taking the oaths of Supremacy, &amp;c., according to the late act of Parliament July 21th 1673 / by Peniston Whalley Esq.</title>
            <author>Whalley, Penistone.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183102</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11981393</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11981393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 523:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The religion established by law, asserted to conduce most to the true interest of prince and subject as it was delivered in a charge, at the general quarter sessions of the peace, held at the borough of Newark, for the county of Nottingham, by adjournment for taking the oaths of Supremacy, &amp;c., according to the late act of Parliament July 21th 1673 / by Peniston Whalley Esq.</title>
                  <author>Whalley, Penistone.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Place ... and Thomas Bassett ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51845:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51845:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RELIGION Eſtabliſhed by Law, aſſerted to conduce moſt to the true Intereſt of Prince and Subject.</p>
            <p>As it was delivered in a Charge, at the General Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Seſſions of the Peace, held at the Borough of <hi>Newark,</hi> for the County of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> by adjournment for taking the Oaths of Supremacy, <hi>&amp;c. July</hi> 21th. 1673.</p>
            <p>According to the late Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Peniſton Whalley</hi> Eſq;</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>I. Eſdr. 3.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Truth overcometh all things.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Place</hi> at <hi>Furnivals</hi>-Inne-Gate in <hi>Holbourn;</hi> and <hi>Thomas Baſſett</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> near <hi>Cliffords</hi>-Inn in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51845:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51845:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did not intend to have given thee the trouble of an <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> very well knowing, that men are not to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by Argument to like any thing of this nature, that they have an averſion from: But that on <hi>Sunday Aug. 24. 1673.</hi> a day as famous in our <hi>Engliſh Kalender,</hi> as the <hi>French,</hi> A <hi>Quaker</hi> came to diſcourſe with me,<note place="margin">There were preſent at the Diſcourſe the chief Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Hundred, the Parſon of the Town, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, beſides others.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout executing the penal Laws, wherein he had a five ſhillings concern: I askt him the reaſon of his opinion, knowing that he had been, a rational <hi>Country-man,</hi> before he fell into thoſe fopperies; He replyed, <hi>That he had a call from above,</hi> and the words were, <hi>Obey the Lord;</hi> and from that hour he turn'd <hi>Quaker,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:51845:3"/>I have reaſon to believe with as much reſolution, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man of any perſwaſion in the world; Now I do not ſee, but its as good an authority as St. <hi>Benets</hi> ſingle Teſtimony of ſeeing his Siſter <hi>Scholaſticas</hi> ſoul go to Heaven: Nay it is as good an Authority, and as <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative</hi> as the <hi>Independents</hi> unintelligible no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about <hi>Converſion, Sanctification</hi> and <hi>Grace;</hi> for they ariſe but from a <hi>ſelf-ſatisfaction</hi> within them, as they ſay, which is no more to be urged to a <hi>ſtranger</hi> then my <hi>Quakers</hi> voice; nor is this the ſingle ſaying of this <hi>Quaker,</hi> but if it be inquired, you will have the like account from most of them, and therefore for ought an indifferent perſon can judg, as good or better au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, witneſſes <hi>Viva Voce</hi> being alwaies of more credit then <hi>Here-ſay evidence,</hi> then the many <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> about the <hi>immaculate conception,</hi> now made an Article of Faith,<note place="margin">Cited by <hi>Stil.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>Bell armin's</hi> viſion to prove auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular confeſſion, or <hi>Urban</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> inſtituting of the Feast of <hi>Corpus Chriſti,</hi> in confirmation of <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> upon the Revelation of a certain woman, or old <hi>Symon Stockes</hi> Revelation from the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> for the habit of the <hi>Carmelites,</hi> or as <hi>John 19th.</hi> inſtituting the Feaſt of all <hi>Souls 1004</hi> upon the
<pb facs="tcp:51845:3"/>dream of the <hi>Abbot Odilo;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex Becan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th. in prol. 4 Lib. Sect.</note> who dreamt that he heard the <hi>Devils</hi> roar for the Souls taken from them by <hi>Maſſes</hi> and <hi>Dirges,:</hi> By this thou mayst eaſily ſee, that moſt of the many differences betwixt <hi>Us,</hi> and the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> with the <hi>Independents,</hi> and their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, are reſolved into <hi>Revelations,</hi> and <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> and ſo of no more Authority to indifferent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons than the <hi>Enthuſiaſms</hi> of the <hi>Quakers;</hi> But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can by no means fall juſtly under ſuch a cenſure, conſidering ſhe is, as we ſay a true <hi>Church,</hi> and acknowledged by all to be ancient, and how all along ſhe has been like <hi>Syon, a City that is at unity in it ſelf;</hi> but that <hi>unity</hi> will not be much admired when this ſhort <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory</hi> of twenty years, commencing <hi>1030</hi> is conſidered: In the <hi>Church</hi> ſate <hi>Benet</hi> the ninth twelve years: <hi>Benet</hi> is depoſed, and <hi>Silveſter</hi> the third comes in by <hi>Symony,</hi> and is expelled by <hi>Benet,</hi> and <hi>he</hi> by the people,<note place="margin">Roſ. Chron.</note> he reſigneth to <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſixth; ſo now three <hi>Popes</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> all depoſed at <hi>Sutrium,</hi> and <hi>Clement</hi> the ſecond choſen, who flyes into <hi>Germany,</hi> and is poyſoned; <hi>Benet</hi> again eight months: And is not here a bleſſed har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for fifteen years; Then <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth ſucceeds
<pb facs="tcp:51845:4"/>five years; but least I ſhould enlarge my volume to the rate of a <hi>Play,</hi> and ſo undo the <hi>Stationer,</hi> I will only tell thee that I gave it in <hi>Charge,</hi> becauſe I thought it my duty, and Printed it, becauſe it may from my hands be more indifferently lookt on, as one known to have no worldly Advantage by the <hi>Church,</hi> then from a known or ſuſpected <hi>Divine,</hi> who will by prejudiced men, which are now too many, be looked upon as partial, and ſo may have a better <hi>effect</hi> then ordinary; for though the world generally be <hi>Sermon</hi>-proof, yet poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly it may not be <hi>Charge</hi>-proof, and that encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged me to make this venture. Yet, becauſe of a thing like a <hi>text,</hi> which like one of your old faſhioned Sermons, <hi>chimes</hi> in every Paragraph, ſome to diſcredit it, will according to their ſcoffing way call it a <hi>Preachment;</hi> well be it ſo, it was neither preached in a Church, nor according to the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and ſo conſequently a <hi>Conventicle,</hi> (a name amongst many ſo ſacred, that it apologizes like <hi>Corban</hi> amongst the <hi>Jews</hi> for omitting the duties of the fifth <hi>commandement</hi>) and ſo then there is no great fear of well coming of; but let all conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles take Example, a thing more revered now than
<pb facs="tcp:51845:4"/>Precepts, and aſſert the Laws and Religion eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as I have done, and its very probable, they may get a bill of comprehenſion, and in the mean time his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Juſtices, I believe, will be unwilling to diſturb them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="charge">
            <pb facs="tcp:51845:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51845:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His being a time that the true Sons of our Church might devoutly wiſh for, but could not Morally few months ago hope ſo ſoon to have ſeen; wherein, as by a Touch-ſtone, gold is diſtinguiſhed from baſer mettals, the true Proteſtant Religion from Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm and Popery, it may not be improper to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to you, by way of <hi>Preamble,</hi> of Religion; and the rather, becauſe you know there are ſo many profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, all pretending to an Equal and Apoſtolical Right.</p>
            <p>Now to enable you the better to diſtinguiſh, I lay this down for a juſt and true meaſure of it, <hi>That Religion is the beſt and ſafeſt, that moſt magnifies God, and likewiſe moſt advances a peaceable Chriſtian converſation amongſt men.</hi> I ſhall not ſay much of the former at preſent, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that all profeſſions equally pretend to it, but make the main ſubject of my diſcourſe concerning the latter. Our bleſſed Lord and Saviour left this for a ſtanding rule to his Church: <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, even ſo do to them:</hi> By the ſtrict following of which, ſo much advancing a <hi>Peaceable Converſation amongst men,</hi> ſhe triumph't o're the <hi>Roman</hi> world in leſs than three hundred years, notwithſtanding the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of all her Legions. The Profeſſours of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51845:6"/>amongſt us, may be reduced to five heads: <hi>Quaker, Independent,</hi> (under which may be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended all the Rabble of Sects, as Familiſts, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Fifth Monarchy men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for Independency is like a Mathematical line, <hi>diviſibilis in ſemper diviſibilia</hi>) <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Papiſt. Now when I have ſet forth the Principles and Practices of all ſeverally, it will not be hard for a Rational unbyaſt man to judge which is the ſafeſt Religion, that is, which moſt advances a peaceable converſation amongſt men.</p>
            <p>The Quaker hath a plauſible pretence, by his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the unlawfulneſs either of Swearing or Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and his practice accordingly, which, if ſo, (as he may very well be ſuſpected to have none, conſidering their being ſtill acted by a light within them) are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely inconſiſtent with Government, and conſequently with peace; which will be eaſily granted when it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that the firſt moment a man turns Quaker, the King loſes a Subject, as to the being uſeful to him, and every man a Neighbour; for he that will not fight in an honourable and juſt War, of which no private perſon is judge, is as dead to his Prince: And likewiſe, he that will not aſſert truth, by oath thereto lawfully called in vindication of his Neighbours Intereſt, there being no other way to do it by the Conſtitution of the Law, is worſe to him. As for their pretenſions to perfection, contrary to Scripture and their own impure practice, I ſhall leave to the Divines to conſider of, and conclude that Quakers <hi>are like ſalt that hath loſt its ſavour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>and thenceforth good for nothing but to be caſt out, and to be trodden under foot of men:</hi> For it is not at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the prudence of Princes, to connive at, much leſs to tolerate an opinion that renders the abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors uſeleſs, if not worſe, to all the ends of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51845:6"/>
            <p> The Independent now pretends to a kind of Call or Election into the Paſtoral Office, as they tearm it, by a Company of people who ſay they are Saints, and that's all the reaſon we have to believe it. I ſhould wonder how it can come into any mans head to accept of an Office, according to their own opinion, ſacred too, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a title (but that we ſee ambitious men will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Power upon any terms) it being a principle in Law, <hi>Nemo poteſt plus juris in alium transferre quam ipſe habet,</hi> None can transfer or give a greater right then he hath. And I think all ſober men will grant, that the people, <hi>viz. Tom, Dick,</hi> and <hi>Cis,</hi> originally have no ſuch power as to confer Holy Orders. <hi>Electo</hi> then may be a fitter name then Paſtor, for thoſe <hi>Boanergeſes.</hi> I have heard of a Garriſon that in a high mutiny, turn'd out the Officers, and choſe out of the Commonalty, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into their rooms, by the name of <hi>Electoes,</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their places in martial conduct, who acted their parts ſtubbornly enough againſt their General, as fearing to return to a private condition, if not worſe. So our pretended Saints have thrown off their Spiritual Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Directors, and have done worſe then the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous <hi>Iſraelites;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 32.23.</note> for they ſo far obſerved the <hi>Decency of Order, as to deſire the High-Prieſt to make them Gods, which ſhould go before them:</hi> But ours have of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves choſe their Gods or <hi>Electoes,</hi> who are not likely to return in haſte to the Communion of the Church, and conſequently to the condition of Private men, being that they exerciſe as abſolute an Epiſcopal and Deſpoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal power, over the Eſtates and Conſciences of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Congregations or Troops of <hi>Bandetti,</hi> as ever any Pope pretended to, in the days of the greateſt Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and <hi>Bigotery;</hi> it being their deſign (I ſuppoſe) to take the Kingdom from men, and to give it to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt; and then the Saints and the ſecret ones ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51845:7"/>work deſtruction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">J. Owen p. 22.165. T. Goodw. P. Nye. Skid. Symſon. W. Bridge. Jer. Burrows Apol to the Parliament.</note> as the ſame Author elegantly hath it. Now what may be the end of that, is not hard to ſay, when a Club of them have jointly declared: <hi>This Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple we carried along with us, not to make our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent judgment and practice a binding Law for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Now if theſe be not as ſlippery Chapmen, by vertue of this, as either the Papiſts with their <hi>Fides non eſt ſervanda cum Haereticis,</hi> Faith is not to be kept with Heretiques; or the Quaker with his <hi>Light within,</hi> I am much miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Now that ſomething has been ſaid of their Principles, 'tis fit you ſhould know likewiſe of their Practices; which have been ſuch, as have not at all ſhamed their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: For all our late Civil War and Bloodſhed, with the never to be too much deplored Fate of the beſt of Kings then, or many ages before living, was the reſult of their moſt holy Faith, and all juſtified by following <hi>Divine Providence;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caryll.</note> and not only ſo, but they perſiſted in their Rebellion to the laſt too, as is evident to all knowing men of that time; nay they were ſo generally involved in it, that <hi>Capua</hi> it ſelf was comparatively loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al:<note place="margin">Sir <hi>W. R.</hi> Hiſt. World. Pun. War. 2.</note> For there were upon a ſtrict ſcrutiny <hi>two</hi> found not guilty of <hi>Rebellion;</hi> but to theſe Gentlemen the ſaying of the Pſalmiſt may be applied, <hi>There is none that doth good, no not one:</hi> And none that is loyal can take the application of that Scripture amiſs, that conſiders, that in the year 1648 a Book was printed and licenſed by the then Authority, with this Title, <hi>Several Speeches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered at a Conference concerning power of Parliament to proceed againſt their King for miſ-government,</hi> which is word for word taken out of <hi>Parſons</hi> the Jeſuites book, as the learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> hath obſerved; which Book was written under the name of <hi>Doleman,</hi> as I take it, to invalidate the <hi>Scotch</hi> ſucceſſion, and conſequently our Kings Title to the Crown of <hi>England:</hi> ſo harmoniouſly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51845:7"/>did the Independent and Jeſuite agree againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy; <hi>Herode</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> were not ſo unanimous in crucifying the Lord of Glory, as theſe were; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably will be again upon occaſion, in quenching the light of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And yet a modern Author,<note place="margin">Rehear. Tranſ.</note> that takes himſelf for no ſmall fool, has the confidence to ſay, that <hi>the Cauſe,</hi> meaning the Rebellion 1642. <hi>was too good to be fought for.</hi> But it may be preſumed by what over acts we ſee of their Allegiance, that had they the ſame opportunity again, they would not have ſo Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable an opinion of it.</p>
            <p>It will not now be difficult from what has been ſaid to conclude, that Independent Principles and Practices notwithſtanding the unintelligible <hi>Jargon</hi> that their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and other printed diſcourſes are full of, are far from making any thing towards a peaceable converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt men, and ſo to be lookt on accordingly. Now what ſeverity ſoever is ſhewed them, muſt come far ſhort (becauſe the Laws are not ſtrict enough for't) of what they have ſhewed to others: For it paſſed for Orthodox amongſt them,<note place="margin">Th. Caſe.</note> 
               <hi>That God would have Judges to ſhew no mercy, when the quarrel was againſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Presbyterians pretend to a conſtant ſucceſſion of Holy Orders or Ordination by impoſition of hands from the Apoſtles time, as well as we, but by the Medium of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, as we of Biſhops. They, that is the ſober part,<note place="margin">Clevel.</note> (for <hi>There is a Church as well as Kirke of Scots</hi>) wave enthuſiaſms and ſuch like dreams, and make the Scripture the rule of Faith, as well as of manners; all the difference then lies in the conſtruction of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which they ſay ſignifies a preaching, ruling, and ſometimes a lay-elder, and our Divines (and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs with more reaſon) ſay a Biſhop, and ſuch an one, as hath ſuperintendency over Presbyters too; but this ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51845:8"/>been the ſubject of the learned pens <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> I ſhall ſay no more, but that many of them are worthy in their generations, and eminent both for Learning and Piety, and have been inſtrumental too in the Kings, and conſequently the Churches Reſtauration; let them now come into her boſome, who is always willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, and reap at leaſt the fruits of thoſe worthy labours, leaſt the controverſie betwixt us and them be decided by a third party, as that of the Mouſe and the Frog in the Fable, was to the ruine of both the gladia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: And I hope there may be an expedient found out for it, for I am ſure the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not of the humor of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth,<note place="margin">Cor. Trid. p. 406.</note> who ſaid, <hi>rather then he would looſe one jot of his due, he would ſee the whole world ruin'd.</hi> It cannot be ſaid, that they were ever immediately guilty of any Soveraign Princes blood, yet they were a little School-men like, too nice in the diſtinction betwixt the Politique and the Perſonal capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of Princes, and did a little too inconſiderately ſwallow the Vulgar Error of the Kings being one of the three<note n="*" place="margin">I humbly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to thoſe worthy perſons of that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether the making the King an Eſtate makes him not a co-ordinate power, and where ſuch is, then in reaſon, all matters are to be decided by majority of ſuffrages, and how that will leſſon Majeſty, he is very ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that cannot diſcern.</note> Eſtates, not having a due regard to the ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of both, which naturally are ſuch as muſt ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the aſſertours of thoſe opinions, liable at leaſt to a ſuſpition that they have been far from being zealous in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that may advance a peaceable converſation amongſt men.</p>
            <p>The next in order is the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe <hi>Credenda,</hi> matters of Faith, are according to the holy Scriptures, and the firſt four general Councils, and are ſuch as all her oppoſers (but the buzzardly Quakers) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, or at leaſt pretend ſo, to be true and Orthodox; ſhe claims a ſucceſſion of Biſhops from the Apoſtles, and hath as much authority for it, notwithſtanding the Fryer-like tale of the Nags-head-Tavern, as any of the moſt potent of her adverſaries; ſhe directs Prayers to God,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51845:8"/>according to his command, and not to the uncertain ear of a Creature interceſſor; in fine, ſhe believes according as they believed, in the pureſt primitive times, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects mens practice accordingly; and though her dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are not ſo ſucceſsful perhaps as then (yet then there were immoralities, as may be ſeen by the irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities in the infant Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and the impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties amongſt the <hi>Nicholaitans</hi> and filthy <hi>Gnoſtiques</hi>) it can no more be attributed to her, then the Idolatry of the old <hi>Iſraelttes</hi> could be to <hi>Moſes,</hi> who directed them otherways. I ſhall not uſe many Arguments, for truth needs not many Champions, but only ſay, That if Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Obedience to Lawful Authority, be an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a peaceable converſation, the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is to be preferred before all others of our Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance; witneſs her brave and patient ſuffering during the almoſt 20 years of tumult and tyranny, in which her ſons aſſerted their allegiance with ſo much chearfulneſs to the loſs of their lives and fortunes, as is not to be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd in any age; to whoſe reſtleſs endeavours and conſtant ſtruglings againſt the pretended powers, his Majeſties happy return may more juſtly be attributed then to any other ſecond Cauſe. Independency it ſelf was not more eminent for Rebellion, then ſhe for Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, which is as inſeparable from her, as light from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; for its as well known as a Negative can be, that never any of her ſons ever made defection, as to that, except one Apoſtate Biſhop (which is the leſs to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, conſidering there was a Judas amongſt the twelve) ſince the Reformation from <hi>Rome;</hi> and though many did pay obedience to the late powers, yet it was for wrath, not conſcience ſake. All this conſidered, it will appear no great wonder, if her ſons be ſtill kindly lookt on by his Majeſty, according to the ſaying of his Royal Unkle to his Cardinal upon another occaſion:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51845:9"/>There was no reaſon he ſhould forſake them that loved him,<note place="margin">Luſt. Ludo. p. 169.</note> to humor the Caprichio's of thoſe that did not love him. So what the Spirit ſaid to the Church of <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> may I hope without preſumption, be applied to that of <hi>England:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe thou haſt kept the word of my patience, I alſo will keep thee from the hour of temptation, which ſhall come upon all the world, to try them that dwell upon the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we come to the Church Triumphant, that of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Grandeur hath o're gone all the Churches that ever were; in the pomp and vanity of this wicked world, ſhe profeſſes the well-bred (that is) the Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Religion, and thinks, I ſuppoſe, that we are as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning in the point of Religion, as we are in that of Cloaths, in love with every thing that is Forraign; ſhe would never offer elſe to impoſe all her little tricks upon us.</p>
            <p>The two Pillars or Staves,<note place="margin">Zec. 11. v. 7.</note> on which this mighty Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine of Popery is ſupported, are not Gods ſtaves of <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and bands,</hi> but Supremacy and Infallibility; Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> was a great Aſſerter of the former, when he made it Authentick Law, in theſe words: <hi>We ſay and define and pronounce, that it is abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, for every humane Creature to be ſubject to the Biſhop of Rome.</hi> A new Article of Faith never heard of amongſt the Ancient Creeds, Antiquity making out the contrary;<note place="margin">Cited by L. Cook Re. 5.</note> For S. <hi>Edw. Laws c.</hi> 19. delivers this for Law, <hi>Rex autem qui vicarius ſummi Regis eſt, ad hoc conſtitutus eſt, ut Regnum &amp; populum Domini, &amp; ſuper omnia ſanctam Eccleſiam regat, &amp; defendat ab inimicis, maleficos autem deſtruat.</hi> By this you may ſee that the King was owned by the Law then to be Gods Vicar or Vicegerent, not foreſeeing the proud decree of <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. Inter omnes convenit, quod nemo poſſit appropriare ullam Eccleſiam cui animarum cura incumbit, cum ſit res
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51845:9"/>Eccleſiaſtica, &amp; Eccleſiaſtica perſonae approprianda, niſi ille qui juriſdictionem habet Eccleſiaſticam; ſed</hi> Gulielmus <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ex ſe, ſine quovis alio Eccleſiarum curam perſonis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticis, ut Rex Angliae appropriavit, unde ipſum Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticam juriſdictionem habuiſſe conſequitur.</hi> It is agreed of all hands, that no man can appropriate any Church with cure of ſouls, becauſe it is wholly an Eccleſiaſtical affair, and to be appropriated to an Eccleſiaſtical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, except one that hath Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction; but <hi>William</hi> the firſt King of <hi>England</hi> did do it, from whence it muſt follow that he had juriſdiction Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical.</p>
            <p>Now if the Kings of <hi>England</hi> had Eccleſiaſtical Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, as it appears they had, by the exerciſing of it, notwithſtanding the decree of a little Council or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle to the contrary, which decreed that <hi>no ſpiritual perſon ſhould enter into any Church by any ſecular perſon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Con. Mant.</note> where was the Popes Almighty Power almoſt, that he pretended to, about that time in every thing?</p>
            <p>By the ancient Laws of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the iſſue born before marriage, is as lawful inheritable, marriage following, as otherways; yet that was never allowed in <hi>England</hi> for all the Popes power, as may appear by the Statute of <hi>Merton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">20 H. 3.</note> when the Biſhops inſtanted the Lords that they would aſſent that the Cuſtome of <hi>England</hi> ſhould conform to that of <hi>Rome,</hi> in that particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this for anſwer, <hi>Nolumus Leges Angliae mutare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cooke 5. Rep.</note> we will not change the Laws of England.</p>
            <p>By this may be ſeen what a ſmall influence the Popes had even at that time upon our Parliament, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the aſſiſtance of the Biſhops, and mitred Abbots.</p>
            <p>Yet afterwards <hi>P. Inno.</hi> 4. occaſionally with a great deal of Magiſterial Indignation (being very angry that <hi>Groſted</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> refuſed a Nephew or nearer Kinſman,<note place="margin">Fox p. 407.</note> for a Prebend of that Church) ſaid that the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51845:10"/>was his Vaſſal,<note place="margin">Mancipium.</note> his Page, his Slave, reflecting I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon that ſubmiſſion that King <hi>John,</hi> as the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Frederick</hi> ſaid in his Letter to <hi>Henry</hi> the third his ſon, more like a woman than a man, made to <hi>Pandolphus</hi> the Legate; yet <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt that Heroick Grandchild of that unfortunate Prince, was of another ſort of mettal, for in his Reign a Subject brought a Bull of <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> againſt another Subject of this Realm, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed it to the Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and this was adjudged Treaſon by the Ancient Common Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> againſt the King, his Crown and Dignity, for which the offender ſhould have been drawn and hang'd; but at the great inſtance of the Chancellor and the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, he was only abjur'd the Realm for ever.</p>
            <p>Certain Meſſengers had from the Pope ſerv'd Proceſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Officer of <hi>Chancery</hi> then held at <hi>York,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. le Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt. f. 224.</note> to command him by thoſe Bulls to appear at <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; for this contempt the party that ſerved the Proceſs, was committed to <hi>York</hi> Caſtle; and at length the Kings Majeſty, by the entreaty of divers great men of the Realm, was content upon taking bond, that he ſhould anſwer the ſaid contempt <hi>ad proximum Parliamentum noſtrum ubicunque illud ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneri contigerit;</hi> at our next Parliament, where ever it happens to be aſſembled or ſummoned, to deliver him out of Priſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt preſented his Clerk to a Benefice within the Province of <hi>York,</hi> who was refuſed by the Arch-Biſhop, for that the Pope by way of Proviſion had conferred it upon another; the King thereupon brought a <hi>Quare non admiſit,</hi> the Biſhop pleaded that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had long time before provided to the ſaid Church, as one having ſupream authority in the Caſe, and that he durſt not, nor had power to put him out; who by the Popes Bull was in poſſeſſion: For which high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt the King, his Crown and Dignity, in refuſing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51845:10"/>to execute his Soveraigns command, fearing to do it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proviſion; by judgment of the Common Law the Lands of his whole Biſhoprick were ſeized into the Kings hands, and loſt during life: So all theſe Preſidents conſidered, it is no wonder if that bold <hi>Briton</hi> who pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh't the Excommunication againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> his time, met with the ſiniſter accident of a Halter.</p>
            <p>For if it be treaſon in a Subject to do ſo againſt a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, as it was adjudged in <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt his time, a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori,</hi> as my Lord <hi>Cooke</hi> ſays, it is treaſon for a Subject to do ſo againſt his Soveraign: It may very well be asked now, conſidering theſe high Practices, and ſome ſtrict Laws to abate the power of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> how the Pope could poſſibly have ſo conſiderable an Intereſt as we know, or at leaſt believe, he had in <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth's time. The Statute of Proviſors of Benefices of 27 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. gives you a reaſon to that time, in theſe words, <hi>That though the Statute of</hi> Ed. 1.25<note n="*" place="margin">Which Statute is not in the printed Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, either by negligence, or probably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was made at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile,</hi> the Roll was not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>ſtands good, yet by ſufferance and negligence, it hath been attempted the contrary.</hi> The Pope afterwards got ground by the remiſs latter end of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third's Reign, and the whole one of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, who though he made the ſtrict Law of <hi>premunire,</hi> yet it did much abate of the ſtrictneſs of the Common Law before ſpoken of, which unhappy Prince was depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and murthered by his Coſen and Vaſſal <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter,</hi> who though the murthered Prince left neither Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren nor Friends, yet by reaſon that the murtherer was not next Heir at Law, he was a little uneaſie all his Reign; ſo that he was forced to comply, by reaſon of the badneſs of his title, contrary to the humor of his great Father, with the ill deſigns of the <hi>Roman Clergy</hi> (who of all are the beſt at ſoldering crackt titles) and make bloody Laws againſt the <hi>Lollards</hi> under the notion of Heretiques;<note place="margin">H. 42. c. 15.</note> yet <hi>Henry</hi> his ſon, who had no fault but his title, let them know
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51845:11"/>other, I will not ſay better things, by ſuppreſſing the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory Aliens, which was all that was done to ſhew the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings in that particular, till <hi>H.</hi> 8. who was, if you peruſe the Chronicles, the firſt that had leaſure to queſtion his Holineſſes encroachments upon this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</p>
            <p>Neither was the Supremacy much more ancient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,<note place="margin">Roſ Hiſt W. Chronolog.</note> for the firſt that had any thing like it was <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, to whom <hi>Phocas</hi> about 606 granted that he ſhould be the head of all Churches; 'twas that <hi>Phocas</hi> that murther'd his Lord and Maſter <hi>Mauritius;</hi> and to ſay the truth, the Popes have arrived to that height they now pretend to by the wickedneſs of Uſurpers, who having no title themſelves, made little regard what they gave to others, to countenance their own Rapine; yet this grant was not ſo authentique as to make the ſucceeding Popes ſtand upon their own legs, for the firſt downright oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of the Emperour, was <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt, who oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Phillipicus</hi> about Images, and not only ſo, but for the greater affront,<note place="margin">Stilling. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. of the Church of Rome. 362.</note> forbad the publique uſe of the Emperours Name and Title, his Succeſſors <hi>Leo</hi> the third and <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond, wrote ſo after his copy, that they ſtript the Emperors of all they had almoſt in <hi>Italy,</hi> by abſolving the Subjects of their Allegiance, that they fell into Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deſtroyed their Provincial <hi>Governours.</hi> The Popes of that time were encouraged to this inſolence by correſpondence with <hi>Charles Martell, Major of the Pallace,</hi> who more then probably had ſome deſign of uſurpation upon the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> at that time managed by a race of weak Princes, which afterwards <hi>Pepin</hi> his ſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by the help of Pope <hi>Zachary,</hi> who underſtanding his meaning when he ſent to know, whether it was not fit for him to bear the name, who did all the buſineſs of a King, readily abſolv'd him of his oath to his Lord and Maſter with all his Nobles and People: <hi>Pepin</hi> upon this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51845:11"/>depoſed his Maſter <hi>Chilperick,</hi> and put him into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, and by ſome ſuch way or worſe, made ſure of the remaining houſe of <hi>Pharamond.</hi> By this may eaſily be ſeen the danger that attends lawful Soveraign Princes by the exorbitant power of the Pope o're the conſciences of their Subjects. The ſucceſſors of this <hi>Zachary,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſuccors that <hi>Pepin</hi> gave them, which needs muſt be very great, having nothing to adjuſt his perjury and uſurpations but the Popes ſupremacy; as on the contrary they had nothing to ſave themſelves from the fury of their juſtly provoked <hi>Leige Lords,</hi> but the ſtrictneſs of that League; yet ſome of his Succeſſors by reaſon of the <hi>Lombarde</hi> power, were not free from trouble; for Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the third was put into Priſon for ſome enormities, and eſcaped to <hi>Charles</hi> into <hi>Saxony,</hi> who brought him to <hi>Rome</hi> with an Army to clear himſelf, where calling a Synod to examine whether the matters were true or no, that he was accuſed of; the bold Pope took the Chair and jollily determined it, <hi>that the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>was above all men, and to be judged by none:</hi> But to make <hi>Charles</hi> amends, he Crowns him and Proelaims him <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and Emperor of the <hi>Romans,</hi> to which he had the ſame title as his Father had to the Kingdom of <hi>France;</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> in requital conquer'd the <hi>Lumbards</hi> for him, and beſtow'd moſt of thoſe Lands upon him, called now the patrimony of the <hi>Church;</hi> for which he was, I ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">Roſ. p. 128.</note> Sainted many years after, having no other vertue but that to deſerve ſuch a favour; and who knows but that ſome kind Pope hereafter may canonize the <hi>Rump-Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or at leaſt the High-Court of Juſtice, they having as much right to do what they did, as <hi>Charles</hi> had to be King of <hi>France</hi> (for the Fathers proſperous treaſon could never create a title in the Son) or <hi>Emperour,</hi> and I am ſure they did the See of <hi>Rome</hi> more ſervice then that great War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier for all his enfeoffing her in thoſe <hi>Italian</hi> Provinces.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51845:12"/>And this is the Original of the Popes greatneſs, who as long as the Empire continued in the line of <hi>Charles</hi> out of common policy, if not gratitude, were very mannerly to the Emperors,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Coun. Tren. 835.</note> for they ſtill dated their Bulls, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Grants, with theſe formal words, <hi>In the Reign of ſuch an Emperour our Lord and Master.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Hildebrand</hi> was of another temper to the <hi>German</hi> Emperours, for he forced <hi>Henry</hi> the Emperour with his Lady and Prince, to attend him three days at the Gates of <hi>Cannuſium,</hi> before he would admit him to his preſence; <hi>Alexander</hi> the third was not much more modeſt, when he ſet his foot upon the Emperour <hi>Frederick</hi> his neck, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely applying that ſaying in the Pſalms, <hi>ſuper Aſpidem &amp; Baſiliſcum ambulabis, &amp; conculcabis Leonem &amp; Draco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this ſubmiſſion was the Emperour forced to ſave the life of his Son, who was lately fallen into his malitious hands by misfortune: But leaſt theſe Examples ſhould by reaſon of their Antiquity be objected againſt, it may not be amiſs to give ſome later inſtances of their being buſie-bodies in managing of Crowns; <hi>Julius</hi> the third very briskly told <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond of <hi>France</hi> in the year 1551.<note place="margin">Con. Trid. 314 <hi>by his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour.</hi> Foul. pag. 725.</note> 
               <hi>That if he took</hi> Parma <hi>from him, he would take</hi> France <hi>from the King;</hi> and in the year 1626 <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the eighth ſent to forbid his beloved ſons the Catholiques of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the taking of the pernicious and unlawful Oath of Allegiance; nay more, the Catholiques of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that unhappy Kingdom to the ſaid <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban,</hi> and after to Pope <hi>Inno.</hi> the tenth, who beſtowed it as a favour upon his deareſt Miſs Madam <hi>Olympia.</hi> In the year 1662 Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Barbarino</hi> bids the <hi>Iriſh</hi> take heed they fall not foul upon ſome things condemned by holy Church, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſting their Loyalty, which they at that time ſtood in need of, conſidering the then poſture of affairs: But theſe however, the latter is a private Doctors opinion, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51845:12"/>the Church not at all anſwerable for it, ſays the little Prieſt that leads the ſilly women captive; for to give them their due, they will never juſtifie any thing but what may conduce to their ends, like them that never tell truth for truths ſake, but becauſe it is fit to be ſo; they give the beſt words of any people in the world to bring people into their Communion, but when once in, they'l ſhew you another manner of Countenance, eſpecially where they have a coercive power, you muſt then believe all their little things upon pain of being deliver'd up to the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar power, that is to <hi>Fire and Fagot,</hi> as it was almoſt in our <hi>Grandfathers</hi> days: and what fair dealing can we expect from them? when the Author of the Hiſtory of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> gives this Character of the Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third, that he was a <hi>Prelate endowed with good qualities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C.T. p. 71.</note> 
               <hi>but among all his Vertues, he made more eſteem of none, then Diſſimulation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to make this more appear, I'le give you a relation of ſome tranſactions of the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> related by a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt, which clearly make out, that, that Holy Office, as he devoutly terms it, did take upon them (and I'me ſure do ſo ſtill, if they do any thing) the cognizance of things, of which, by their firſt inſtitution they were not at all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Judges; that Office or Court was ſet up at the inſtance of <hi>Dominick</hi> (whoſe Mother dreamt when ſhe was with Child of him,<note place="margin">Martyr. in vit. Dom.</note> that ſhe had a whelp vomiting fire in her womb) to reduce the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> about the year 1205, and afterwards brought into <hi>Spain</hi> upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Granada</hi> by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and <hi>Iſabella</hi> Kings of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon</hi> and <hi>Caſtile,</hi> as an expedient of diſcrimination of Chriſtians from <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Moors:</hi> But <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth made other uſe of it in the Low Countries, for by its help he burnt and otherways deſtroyed 50000 of his poor Subjects, little thinking that his memory, as well as the perſons, of his moſt inward friends ſhould fall under their laſh.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51845:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The Story lies thus, which for the Novelty I have tranſlated.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Amongſt all the Reports that had been raiſed in the world concerning the ſaid Emperour,<note place="margin">Vite Don Carlo.</note> 
                  <hi>viz. Charles</hi> the fifth's retreat, the ſtrangeſt was, that the continual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce he had with the <hi>German</hi> Proteſtants inclined him to their opinions, and that he had retired himſelf only that he might have liberty to end his days in the exerciſes of piety, conformable to his ſecret diſpoſitions; it was ſaid he could not forgive himſelf the ill uſage which ſo many brave Princes of that party, which the chance of war had put into his power, had received from him, their Vertue, which in their greateſt unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs ſhamed his fortune, had inſenſibly rais'd in his ſoul ſome ſort of eſteem for their opinions; he durſt no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger condemn a Religion, to which ſo great perſons thought it their duty to ſacrifice all that mankind holds moſt pretious: this eſteem appeared by the choice that he made of perſons much ſuſpected of Hereſie, for his ſpiritual conduct,<note place="margin">C.T. p. 417. <hi>call'd his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions</hi>
                  </note> as Dr. <hi>Ca Calla</hi> his preacher, the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> and above all <hi>Conſtantius Ponce</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Droſſe</hi> his Director.</p>
               <p>It hath been ſince known, that in the <hi>Cell</hi> in which he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at St <hi>Juſt,</hi> was filled of all ſides with writings, wrote by his own hand, upon <hi>Juſtification and Grace,</hi> which were not much different from the opinion of the <hi>Novelliſts;</hi> but nothing ſo much confirmed this Report, as his Will, there were no pious Legacies, nor <hi>foundations</hi> for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as made it ſo different from thoſe of the zealous <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks,</hi> that the <hi>Inquiſition of Spain</hi> thought they had reaſon to be offended at it; they durſt not for all that break out before the Kings arrival, but that Prince ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſignalized his firſt coming into the Country, by the death of all Abettors of the new opinion, the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> becoming bolder by his Example, firſt attacht the Arch-Biſhop
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51845:13"/>of <hi>Toledo,</hi> then the Emperors <hi>Preacher,</hi> and at laſt <hi>Conſtant Ponce;</hi> the King ſuffering them all to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, the people lookt upon his patience as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of his zeal for the true Religion: but all the reſt of Europe ſaw with horror, the Confeſſor of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth the Emperor, in whoſe arms the Prince had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, and who had as it were received that great Soul into his boſome, delivered by the hands of his own Son, to the moſt cruel and ſhameful of all puniſhments. In fine, the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> in the proceſs, having accuſed the ſaid perſons to have had their hands in the Emperors Will, they had the boldneſs to condemn them with it to the fire: The King awakned at this Sentence, as with a <hi>Clap of Thunder,</hi> at firſt the envy that he bore to the glory of his Father, made him take pleaſure in ſeeing his memory expoſed to this affront; but having more maturely conſidered the conſequences of the attempt, he by the ſafeſt and ſecureſt ways that he could chooſe, hindred the effects of it, that ſo he might ſave the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Holy Office,</hi> and make no breach in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Tribunal;</hi> in ſhort, the Dr. <hi>Ca Calla</hi> was burnt alive, and with him the Effigies of <hi>Conſtant Ponce,</hi> dead ſome days before in Priſon: the King was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſuffer the execution, that ſo he might oblige the Holy Office to conſent, that the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>C. Tr. ibid.</hi> He had not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, his profits ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on for life, ſo its humbly conceived that the vaſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of that See were the beſt mediatours for that unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</note> might appeal to <hi>Rome,</hi> and that there might be no more ſpeech about the <hi>Emperors</hi> laſt Will &amp; Teſtament.</p>
            </q>
            <p>But they left not there, for taking advantage of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulouſneſs of that <hi>Prieſt-Peckt</hi> Prince <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond; they never left impoſing upon him that <hi>Don Carlo</hi> his ſon was dangerous to his Eſtate, and intimated too much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with his Mother in Law; ſo that at length, the Prince, though heir apparent to the <hi>Crown,</hi> for ſhewing too indiſcreet an indignation at that affront to his Grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers memory, and ſome other demonſtrations of his ill
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51845:14"/>ſentiments of their tyranny, was given up to them, who did him only the favour to give him the choice of his death: the miſchief ended not there neither, for the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Prince in a manner commanded his <hi>Queen,</hi> though great with <hi>Child,</hi> to be poyſoned, to expiate the ſuppoſed Crime<note n="*" place="margin">How far that Office had to do in it, I'le not determine; but its no great breach of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to think, that thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who would not ſpare the Heir apparent of his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Majeſty, would not be very ſcrupulous in attempting upon Heretical Princes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when the Inquiſition preferred that barbarous and unnatural mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Don Carlo,</hi> before the obedience of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and in a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Zeal compared the King, all with one voice, to the Eternal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who had not ſpared his own Son for the ſalvation of mankind; now what ſins will not they paſs by for the advance of the Papal authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when ſo black a crime has got ſuch an extravagant <hi>encomium.</hi>
               </note>: There was a deſign upon the Queen of <hi>Navarre</hi> and her ſon, after ward <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France,</hi> to ſeize them when they lived at <hi>Pan,</hi> by the villany of one Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Dominick</hi> a <hi>Bernois,</hi> but by the kindneſs of the Queen before mention'd, the generoſity of <hi>Don Carlo</hi> concurring, which might be one thing that coſt her her life; it was diſcover'd, but what they failed in at that time, their Factors afterwards brought to paſs upon one with a <hi>knife,</hi> and upon the other with <hi>poyſon;</hi> by this you may ſee what they would be at, none muſt make a <hi>Will,</hi> except they have a ſhare, or elſe his memory muſt be expoſed to contempt and ſcorn; for had the Emperor given according to his quality, a good ſum of money for <hi>foundations</hi> for <hi>prayers,</hi> as my Author terms it, the <hi>Will</hi> nor any thing elſe had been queſtioned, and the Dr. had eſcaped <hi>Spitchcocking,</hi> and though the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> is a ſtranger in moſt of the <hi>Popiſh Countries,</hi> yet this abates but little of the force of my argument, for who knows not that it is none of the <hi>Popes</hi> fault? When<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>C.T.</hi> 405.416. De ſeres in vita H. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth ſaid that it was the principal <hi>ſecret and myſtery of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> and at his laſt gaſp recommended it to the <hi>Cardinals,</hi> exhorting them to <hi>eſtabliſh it where ever they could;</hi> and his Succeſſors have always been ready to ſhew their good will to it, witneſs the endeavours to introduce it into <hi>France,</hi> by vertue of the <hi>Holy League,</hi> under the miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that bloody and perfidious <hi>Prince</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and afterwards of his Brother the <hi>Duke de Main:</hi> How many horrid murders were perpetrated in order to it? but above all, the murder of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, by a <hi>Jacobin Monk</hi> at St. <hi>Cloud,</hi> is moſt admirable, for in the ſame room
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51845:14"/>at St. <hi>Cloud,</hi> where he amongſt others had contrived the bloody Maſſacre at <hi>Paris,</hi> the greateſt piece of villany and treachery that the world ever knew juſtified (except that of the <hi>Mamertines,</hi> upon their hoſts at <hi>Meſſana</hi>) was ſlain by a Monk for not being papiſt enough,<note place="margin">Sir W. R. l. 1.270.</note> though he had formerly ſo ſignalized it, by an Act ſo <hi>Heroique,</hi> that his <hi>Holineſs</hi> thought fit to celebrate, by calling his Cardinals together, to give <q>
                  <hi>God thanks for ſo great a bleſſing confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the Roman See, and the Chriſtian World.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To omit many more notorious practices, it's very prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are inconſiſtent with Monarchy, for it ſets up at the beſt two Supreams, like <hi>Hobs his two omnipotents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">DeCive.</note> which will like them too, be in a continual ſtate of <hi>diſobedience</hi> to each other, which is utterly inconſiſtent with the ends of <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we have a great deal of reaſon to ſubmit, which they call <hi>reconciling</hi> our ſelves to the <hi>See of Rome,</hi> when we conſider how the <hi>Council of Conſtance</hi> broke the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique faith, in burning of <hi>John Hus and Hierom of Prague,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. T.</note> and as the <hi>Diet at Wormes</hi> would have done in the caſe of <hi>Luther,</hi> had not the <hi>Prince Palatine Lewis,</hi> uſed his power as well as reaſons againſt it; and no wonder, when it is conſidered what <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 20.1555. in the <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> after wards declared, a mongſt other things, that it is an article of Faith <q>
                  <hi>That the Pope cannot be bound, and much leſs can bind himſelf,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C.T. 396.</note> 
                  <hi>and that to ſay otherwiſe is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt hereſie, and if any after that ſhould ſay ſo, the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhould proceed.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſay much of <hi>Infallibility,</hi> their ſecond <hi>Staff or Pillar,</hi> becauſe the pretences to it (one would think) cannot be very ſtrong, when you conſider that there have been about 30 Schiſms in that <hi>Church,</hi> that is more then one Pope at a time, and <hi>Council</hi> againſt <hi>Council</hi> too in the Caſe, as that of <hi>Baſil</hi> under <hi>Felix</hi> the fifth, againſt <hi>Florence</hi> under <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, beſides others, and all equally
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51845:15"/>pretending, and I think with equal right too, to <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> which is not much ſtrengthned by the Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament that declared,<note place="margin">2 R. 2. c. 5.</note> that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban was duly choſen Pope, and ſo ought to be accepted and obeyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Image worſhip,</hi> I ſhall wave as being (by an able Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of our Church, ſufficiently proved to be Idolatry, notwithſtanding the nice diſtinctions of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Stilling. of Idol.</note> and ſhall ſpeak firſt of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> as being the greateſt, if not the only part of their Religion, that they are content to have the Scriptures extant for, but with what reaſon we ſhall briefly examine [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>this is my body</hi>) it is here obſervable that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not the Relative to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ham. annot. Mat. 28.</note> 
               <hi>bread,</hi> but of the <hi>neuter gender,</hi> and conſequently it is not here ſaid, that this bread is my body (the body of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) but either indefinitely <hi>this,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>take, eat, this is my body;</hi> this taking or eating is, or denotes my body, which is more fully expreſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. <hi>This is my body which is given for you, do this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance or commemoration of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many other arguments made uſe of thereby this Learned Doctor, to whom I refer thoſe that deſire further ſatisfaction in this point, whereby he does inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate the <hi>literal</hi> and <hi>carnal</hi> meaning of theſe words ſo far, as you may as ſoon prove <hi>Extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> by them as <hi>Tranſubstantiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now having done with the <hi>Scriptural</hi> part of it,<note place="margin">Acts &amp; Mon. 218.</note> it may not be amiſs to tell you, that it is but a <hi>Novel,</hi> being but eſtabliſhed under Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the ſecond, againſt <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius</hi> in the Council of <hi>Lateran:</hi> Yet <hi>Hildebrand</hi> his Succeſſor had no great faith in it, though ſo eſtabliſhed, when he deſired the Church to pray that God would ſhew by miracle whether <hi>Berengarius</hi> was rightly condemned or no, an argument of his doubting; but after he gave a ſpecial one, that he no longer doubted, though I cannot ſay it was any great argument of <hi>Faith,</hi> when in a fit of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51845:15"/>madneſs he burnt the <hi>Host,</hi> becauſe it did not give an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer concerning the ſucceſs of <hi>Henry the Emperor:</hi> But ſince that doctrine, with a great many other worthy ones, hath been confirmed by the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Con. Tr. Seſ. 13.</note> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed that <hi>Divine honor ſhould be given to the Bread.</hi> But no wonder if you conſider the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Quinque Eccleſiae</hi>'s Letter, an eminent member of the Council, to the Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Maximilian</hi> the ſecond; <q>
                  <hi>What good</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>could be done in that Council, where Votes were not weighed but numbred;</hi> and a little after, <hi>They were hireling Biſhops, who as Country Bagpipes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">C.T. 84.</note> 
                  <hi>could not ſpeak but as breath was put into them, the holy Ghoſt had nothing to do in this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</hi>
               </q> For it conſiſted of <hi>Tituladoe's, Beardleſs boys, old flatterers, unlearned and ſimple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>yet fitted by their impudent boldneſs;</hi> generals of orders, names, nor things ever heard of in the primitive time, but they are the <hi>Popes Mamalukes,</hi> with whom he doth <hi>enſlave</hi> a great part of the <hi>world,</hi> and deſigus the ſame to the reſt.</p>
            <p>Now if the point of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> for which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine honor is given to the bread, come to be examined by <hi>reaſon,</hi> which is not wholly to be declined in matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> it will notwithſtanding the Fathers of <hi>Trent,</hi> be found little leſs then a meer Invention: God Almighty requires a <hi>reaſonable ſervice</hi> of us, 'tis then impious to think that we muſt wave that faculty, by which we are diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Brutes,</hi> in becoming his ſervants, as all men muſt, that believe that Doctrine: And though they pretend that the doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> is as irreconcilable to reaſon, as the other, and yet not to be diſputed; they may as well argue thus, the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> is not to be comprehended by reaſon, <hi>Ergo</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> is <hi>Infallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Peter</hi> on the day of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> uſed other kind of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, when 3000 were converted; for if he had ſaid,<note place="margin">Acts 2. from v. 6.</note> inſtead of <hi>God hath made the ſame Jeſus whom ye have cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified both Lord and Chriſt:</hi> that the <hi>wafer</hi> or <hi>piece</hi> of bread
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51845:16"/>then ſhewed them, was the ſame <hi>Jeſus</hi> that not many days before was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> what would a rational man think would have been the ſequel, they would have counted him at the beſt, as they did the Eleven, <hi>full of new wine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 13.</note> nay rather ſome of the <hi>Zealots</hi> would have ſtoned him, as they afterwards did St. <hi>Stephen</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> upon a leſs occaſion: Therefore no wonder if the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> ſo often miſcarry amongſt the <hi>Japaneſes,</hi> a very wiſe and rational people, when the ſtrongeſt arguments to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> conſiſt in carrying a bit of <hi>bread</hi> in proceſſion and <hi>worſhipping</hi> it.</p>
            <p>I'le give you one <hi>Philoſophical</hi> argument for all out of Father <hi>Gage</hi> a late converted <hi>Dominican,</hi> hoping it may be as lawful for me to have a <hi>Batt</hi> at the <hi>Pope</hi> with the <hi>Butt end</hi> of a <hi>Dominican,</hi> as it was for <hi>Merry Andrew</hi> to have one at the <hi>Church of England</hi> with the <hi>Butt end</hi> of an <hi>Arch-Biſhop;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rehearſal tranſproſed.</note> and that's thus, <q>When Mr. <hi>Gage</hi> was at <hi>Portabello</hi> in his return for <hi>England</hi> from the <hi>West Indies,</hi> as he was celebrating <hi>Maſs,</hi> and being devout in his <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento</hi> prayer,<note place="margin">Survey of the Weſt Indies. 197.</note> a mouſe came and ſtole away the <hi>Wafer,</hi> which being recovered from her by the help of ſome Prieſts, though half eaten up, was a great motive for him to rub up his <hi>Philoſophy</hi> concerning <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> and ſo reſolved (as any reaſonable man would) that what was eaten up by the mouſe, was no <hi>accident</hi> but a real <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> which no Papiſt will be willing to ſay was the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>Chriſts body</hi> (becauſe of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd conſequence) <hi>Ergo,</hi> it muſt follow it was the <hi>ſuſtance</hi> of bread, and ſo no <hi>Tranſubstantiation:</hi> Beſides it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the <hi>Philoſophical Axiome, Duo contradictoria non poſſunt ſimul &amp; ſemel de eodem verificari,</hi> two contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions cannot be verified both together, and at the ſame time, for here in <hi>Romes</hi> Judgment, the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was gnawn and eaten, and in another place it was not <hi>gnawn</hi> and <hi>eaten.</hi>
               </q> To this purpoſe <hi>Father Gage,</hi> and rightly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51845:16"/>too; For nothing is more abſurd then this Doctrine, for it implies <hi>contradictions,</hi> which are reconcilable neither to right <hi>reaſon</hi> nor to <hi>omnipotency</hi> it ſelf, for that can do any thing but lye, that is, act <hi>contradictions:</hi> They'le tell you of many <hi>miracles</hi> about it, but the greateſt I believe i'th caſe is, that men, otherwiſe of great <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>learning,</hi> ſhould ſo much deny their ſenſe and reaſon, as to believe ſuch a <hi>notoriety</hi> of contradictions and fopperies: And to compleat the abſurd conſequences of it,<note place="margin">Dean Tillot. ſon.</note> our ſenſes are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived too in their object, and that at a due diſtance; and if they be to be impoſed upon in theſe <hi>circumstances,</hi> all and at the ſame time, their's an end of all <hi>argumentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, that opinion is hazardous even accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their own principles, for 'tis decreed under an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema, That the Miniſters intention is neceſsary to the eſſence of Sacraments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C.T. Seſſ. 7. Can. 11.12.</note> and that <hi>the Miniſter who is in mortal ſin giveth not the true Sacrament,</hi> and that certainly made the condition of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh <hi>Emperour,</hi> very <hi>lamentable,</hi> being <hi>poyſon'd</hi> by a <hi>predicant Fryer</hi> in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and <hi>damned</hi> too, for committing <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in worſhiping the <hi>elements,</hi> for though the Prieſt might have a right <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the conſecration, yet no man can excuſe him from <hi>mortall</hi> ſin in the <hi>Execution</hi> of ſo <hi>nefandous an act;</hi> but it may be objected that the <hi>Pope</hi> who was then at enmity with the <hi>Emperour</hi> directed it, and then the intention was right, and no <hi>mortal</hi> ſin in the <hi>Priest</hi> neither; and ſo the good <hi>Emperour</hi> that was <hi>poiſon'd</hi> in the ſimplicity of his heart, might get to <hi>Heaven,</hi> eſpecially if the <hi>Pope</hi> would have put to his helping hand, as he did to <hi>Father Garnet</hi> the <hi>gunpowder</hi> man, who died in a worſe cauſe, thought not ſo much out of the <hi>Popes</hi> favour;<note place="margin">Fullers Ch. Hiſt. l. 10. p. 41.</note> and ſo the heavenly <hi>Crown</hi> would make him ample amends for the loſs of his <hi>Earthly.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51845:17"/>
            <p> And here I cannot but admire the great Prudence and Piety of the late Act of Parliament, which I know has been much miſconſtrued by the malice of ſome, and weakneſs of others, who ſeem to intimate that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has declared the Sacrament to be meer bread and wine, according to the opinion of the Sacramentaries, which is moſt contrary both to the words of the Act and the Doctrine of our Church; for the words are theſe, <hi>I do believe that there is not any</hi> Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, or in the Elements of Bread and Wine, at, or after the Conſecration thereof by any perſon whatſoever;</hi> which clears the point to the meaneſt capacity, that nothing is affirmed, nor nothing denied but <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> Not <hi>Con-ſubſtantiation</hi> it ſelf, the known opinion of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches, although as little believed amongſt us as the other; ſo that it is evident that this Act, pen'd with all the modeſty that became dutiful Sons of our Church, and the wiſdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting moſt worthy Patriots, was not intended to define Doctrines, but to diſtinguiſh perſons.</p>
            <p>The next point to be examined is <hi>Praying</hi> to <hi>Saints,</hi> crept into the <hi>Church</hi> before, but confirmed by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 590. which is not only againſt the command of God, but more then probably loſt labour, for the Scripture tells us, that <hi>Abraham knows us not, and Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el is ignorant of us,</hi> and 'tis rational to believe that they are in as great a ſtate of <hi>Bliſs,</hi> as <hi>Tho. Becket, Dominick,</hi> St. <hi>Francis,</hi> or <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> who was a Gentleman of ſuch behaviour, that a <hi>Country Juſtice,</hi> and no <hi>Adam Overdoe</hi> neither, would have whipt for his good breeding, as any body will believe that peruſes the life of that glorious <hi>Saint,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stilling. Fan. 273.</note> and indeed ſo it was done by a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Governor, to meliorate his underſtanding in the <hi>Ethiques</hi> of putting off his hat to a <hi>Magiſtrate:</hi> yet all are ſolved by <hi>miracles,</hi> which are ſuch that all the <hi>Romances from Grand Cyrus to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51845:17"/>Tom Thumb</hi> put together, compared to them, may paſs for <hi>Claſſical</hi> hiſtory: To omit the 200 <hi>miracles</hi> wrought by <hi>Ignatius</hi> after his death, I'le give you a ſhort ſtory out of <hi>Father Creſſy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ch. Hiſt. 195.</note> St. <hi>Piran fed ten Iriſh Kings and their Armies with three Cows; raiſed dead men and dead pigs to life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I wonder what ſhould come into his <hi>politique</hi> pate, to ſtuff a book with ſuch <hi>Tales</hi> as theſe, in order to the propagating any opinion ſoever, now <hi>Miracles</hi> being commonly wrought at the <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> or by the merit of ſome <hi>Saint</hi> or other, adjuſt the praying to them; but they being ſuch as are greater then any that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> or our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf did, and to no purpoſe commonly, as St. <hi>Bennets</hi> mending a Sieve by miracle to ſave two pence,<note place="margin">Ex leg. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Ben.</note> and throwing the <hi>Helve</hi> after the <hi>Hatchet</hi> into the water, miraculouſly bringing them together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain (which either made good or gave occaſion for the Proverb) may juſtly bring them under the ſuſpition of <hi>Romances,</hi> not to ſay worſe; many tricks have been done by combination, which have amazed the credulous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not having the priviledge or opportunity, or perhaps skill, for an Inquiſition or ſearch, and therefore paſs among ſome devout ones (that have more Faith then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) for miracles of the firſt <hi>Magnitude:</hi> To omit the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ones I will give you one of a late date.<note place="margin">Frier. Egan. Fran. conv. p. 15.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>About ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years ago, a Prieſt nigh Limbrick named William Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel had for</hi> 50. <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> hired a woman to pretend her ſelf a Criple from her birth, and that ſhe had a Revelation; that if ſhe dipt her ſelf in ſuch a Well, whilst a Prieſt ſaid Maſs by the place, ſhe ſhould be recovered; The Plot thus laid and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed ſhe comes halting to the Well, but returns out of it perfectly ſound, which was a miracle to the people, and got the contriver a great Sum of mony, and confirmed many in their Superſtition: after ſome time the woman had ſome remorſe of conſcience and came to the Author of this Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, o confeſſion, in order to abſolution, which he would not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51845:18"/>grant, till an accompt of the cheat ſhould be given to the Congregation, which ſhe did accordingly.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Yet for matter of Fact, againſt which there's no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they will tell you,<note place="margin">Mat. Paris 880 Lew. 9.</note> both out of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and by daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience too, that many have been recovered out of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſickneſſes by having a piece of the <hi>Holy Croſs,</hi> or ſome other<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>But of all <hi>reliques</hi> the moſt admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is the Hem of the <hi>Carpenter Joſeph</hi> incloſed in a Set of boxes, to be ſeen at <hi>Nints</hi> in <hi>Britany,</hi> the firſt a Wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot, within that a Silver box, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that a golden, or guilt box, within that a Chryſtal box, conteining a wooden plain one, viſible through the Chryſtal which conteins the Holy Hem, and reaſon enough for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny boxes; for if it ſhould get looſe after ſo many hundred of years con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement it would be as boiſtrous as the Liquor ſo fam'd by a Poet of our own, when,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It bounces, foams, and froths, and flitters</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As it were troubled with the Squitters.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <bibl>Virg. Traveſty l. 1.</bibl>
               </note> 
               <hi>Relique</hi> applyed to them and therefore thoſe things are not to be derided: In anſwer; I will give you the reply of <hi>Diagoras</hi> of <hi>Samothrace</hi> to a friend weakly though truly arguing for providence, from the pictures of a great many perſons hung up in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Temple,</hi> that had by prayers eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Ship-wrack;<note n="*" place="margin">Pet. Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. in Diog. Laer. an imad. p. 739.</note> 
               <hi>Ita fuit, illi enim nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam picti ſunt qui naufragium fecerunt, in marique perierunt:</hi> Very likely; for there are no pictures for them who have ſuffred Shipwrack, and are loſt in the Sea; So they generally apply to all ſick perſons, ſome relique or other, and if any live, 'tis forſooth by the <hi>merit</hi> and <hi>interceſſion</hi> of ſome <hi>Saint</hi> or other, but if the party dye, then no ſtory of the <hi>Application;</hi> Paralel to this the <hi>Portugals</hi> have a cuſtom, after praying to St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> to give them a good wind, to attempt, or bind a little <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> but commonly upon the <hi>Pilot</hi>'s interceſſion, who paſſes his word for the <hi>Saint,</hi> telling them, <hi>he is ſo honeſt he will do it without being bound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Travels of Ped della val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le into the E. Indies. p. 550.</note> they forbear; <hi>A barbarous ſuperstition</hi> (ſays my Author) <hi>but yet ſuch as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times through the Faith, and ſimplicity of thoſe that practiſe it uſes to be heard,</hi> a very worthy obſervation and fit for Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> viii. his <hi>Chamberlain</hi> of honor:<note place="margin">ibid. pag. 218.</note> As the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> had their particular Gods, for particular things, as <hi>Cuna</hi> for Cradles, <hi>Hebe</hi> for Youth, <hi>Morpheus</hi> for Sleep, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51845:18"/>ſo they with an equal reaſon, as well as devotion, have their Saints for particulars, as to offices, perſons, diſeaſes, callings, Countrys, and brute Animals too, as St. <hi>Patrick</hi> for <hi>Ireland,</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> for Painters, Sr. <hi>Hubert</hi> for hunters, St. <hi>Gertrude</hi> for Rat-catchers, St. <hi>Clare</hi> for ſore Eyes, St. <hi>Roch</hi> for Coblers, St. <hi>Iue</hi> for Lawyers, St. <hi>Gallus</hi> for Geeſe, derogating thereby from the worth and honor of thoſe bleſſed <hi>Saints,</hi> as if they could not, and that implys <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> or, as if they would not, and that implies <hi>ſpight,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignly concern themſelves in the general affairs of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>One eſpecial <hi>Argument</hi> they have for the truth of their Religion, eſpecially againſt us, the many ſeverities, in order to mortification that many of their orders impoſe upon themſelves, but if they would conſider, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are quite out-done by the <hi>Chineſe</hi> and other <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Idolaters,</hi> and that <hi>Baals Prieſts</hi> had no great applauſe from the <hi>Prophet</hi> for the like, they would not much preſs that point: <hi>Lucian</hi> tells us of ſtrict <hi>ſeverities,</hi> that the <hi>Priests</hi> of <hi>Hieropolis</hi> a Town in <hi>Syria</hi> were guelded, Now if there was ſo ſharp a ceremony to their admittance into <hi>England,</hi> It would keep this Land as ſafe from them, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> as the <hi>flaming Sword</hi> did <hi>Eden</hi> from our <hi>Anceſtors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I hinted the moſt conſiderable <hi>Doctrines</hi> of that <hi>Church,</hi> for <hi>Purgatory, Prayers for the dead, Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> or <hi>Pardons</hi> for <hi>forty thouſand years to come</hi> ſometimes, are but, as indeed many of the reſt, the wanton <hi>excreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies</hi> of <hi>Infallibility</hi> which was not in Pope <hi>Alex.</hi> vi. when he was poyſoned by miſtaking the cup of Wine, that he and his hopeful Son <hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi> had prepared to poyſon Cardinal <hi>Carnete</hi> with. I will now ſuperadd a little of their <hi>Principles</hi> of morality, which are ſuch as cannot be grateful to Society; for the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have ſound out a way by directing the <hi>intention</hi> to ſanctify the moſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51845:19"/>
               <hi>Flagitious</hi> act imaginable, I will not excuſe their other orders neither, for a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> lately converted declares thus,<note place="margin">F. Egan.</note> 
               <hi>I thought it a meritorious action to murder either Prince or Proteſtant Subject, provided I was commiſſioned ſo to do by the Pope:</hi> And this cannot be concluded to be a ſingle opinion, when one conſiders the Aſſaſinations of the two <hi>Henrys</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> though <hi>Papists;</hi> the many at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts upon Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon,</hi> and the late <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> none of which was ever yet by any Publique inſtrument of that Church diſavow'd Now comparing all what has been ſayd together, it will be eaſy to determin what <hi>Religion makes moſt for a peaceable converſation,</hi> and that I am ſure is the true <hi>Intereſt</hi> both of <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People:</hi> Now conſidering what hath been diſcourſt on, you will conclude I ſuppoſe, that penal <hi>Laws</hi> about <hi>Religion</hi> will be given in <hi>Charg,</hi> which ſome kind natur'd man, may perhaps ſay were made only <hi>in terro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> and therefore not to be ſtrictly executed, but as that is but a weak <hi>Argument</hi> to defend thoſe <hi>Felonies,</hi> that are made ſo by <hi>Statute,</hi> ſo ought it not to be of more force here, for the Magiſtracy is rationably in point of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, though there was no other obligation bound to do it: For the <hi>Congregations</hi> or troupes of <hi>Diſsenters</hi> fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling every day by reaſon of the <hi>Itching</hi> ears of the <hi>Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Independants</hi> may poſſibly encourage their <hi>Ledders</hi> by their number (that being the ordinary way to take meaſures of ſtrength by) to attempt upon the <hi>Government,</hi> which we have reaſon to think not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, when the attempt of <hi>Venner</hi> and his complices with that of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> a tribe of the <hi>Independents</hi> upon <hi>Germany,</hi> is conſidered; and all <hi>Caſuists</hi> do agree, it is as lawful to levy war againſt this <hi>King,</hi> as it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Father,</hi> and though ſomething may be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for thoſe Sects, if any ſuch be amongſt us, that like the * <hi>Bramans,</hi> or <hi>Banians</hi> amongſt the <hi>Eaſt Indians</hi> hold
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51845:19"/>it ſin to deſtroy any creature though of never ſo <hi>miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous</hi> a kind, and ſtrictly practiſe it even in their diet, yet nothing can be ſaid for ſuch, who like the <hi>Mahometan Dervices</hi> hold it an acceptable ſervice to <hi>God,</hi> if not <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious,</hi> to deſtroy any perſon of an <hi>erroneous perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as they count all who are not of their <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as at the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Clermont</hi> about the holy War,<note place="margin">Holy W. c. 8. l. 1.</note> the whole aſſembly ſaid, <hi>God</hi> willeth it, ſo to encourage you further in your preſentments, the <hi>Bench</hi> ſays, the <hi>King willeth it,</hi> which is ſufficiently made out, when you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, for as there is no ordinary way of knowing <hi>Gods Will,</hi> but by the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> So the moſt proper way of knowing the <hi>Kings will,</hi> eſpecially at this <hi>Diſtance</hi> is by his <hi>Laws;</hi> from whence is that <hi>Principle</hi> in Law that the <hi>King can do no wrong,</hi> becauſe he is ſtill preſumed to act the <hi>Law,</hi> which is the only true <hi>Standard</hi> of wrong and <hi>right.</hi> 'Tis true it was a <hi>maxime</hi> amongſt the <hi>Civilians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ulpian.</note> when the <hi>Government</hi> was arbitrary, <hi>Quicquid placuit Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi, legis habet vigorem,</hi> Whatſoever pleaſes the King, has the force and vigor of a Law: But ſuch is the happy conſtitution of our <hi>Government,</hi> his <hi>Majeſties Grace</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring that it may paſs for a <hi>Maxime</hi> in <hi>England; Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid eſt lex, Placet Regi,</hi> whatſoever is Law pleaſeth the <hi>King,</hi> which his <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath ſufficiently <hi>evidenced,</hi> by not attempting in the leaſt, upon either Religion, or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty;</hi> The <hi>Laws</hi> being the King of <hi>Englands Edicts,</hi> by which he reigns more in the hearts of his, then others o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>fortunes</hi> of their Subjects.</p>
            <p>You are therefore to preſent <hi>Recuſants</hi> of all ſorts, becauſe diſobedient to the <hi>Laws,</hi> under which we enjoy more happineſs than any Nation whatſoever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
